Guide to the Charles Montague Bakewell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Montague Bakewell papers
1897-1928
1916-1920
MS 765
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
The papers consist of philosophical writings, lecture notes, and teaching materials documenting Charles Bakewell's career as professor of philosophy at Yale University. His role as a political and civic leader in Connecticut, and his continuing relationship with New Haven's Italian community, can also be traced in political addresses, and in miscellaneous notes. Also included are documents, research materials, and sixteen volumes of photographs depicting the work of the American Red Cross in Italy during World War I, supporting his 1920 publication The Story of the American Red Cross in Italy.
Bakewell, Charles M. (Charles Montague), 1867-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Bakewell to the Yale University Library in 1932 and transferred from stacks in 1990 and 2004. Gift of Charles Bakewell in 1945. Gift of Henry P. Bakewell and Mildred Bakewell Hooker in 1958. Transferred from Lawrance Hall in 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Material in Series II may be used only with the permission of Mildred Bakewell Hooker, daughter of Charles Bakewell.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and two additions: I. Correspondence, 1901-1947 [returned at donor's request in 1979]. II. Writings and Miscellany, 1897-1928. III. Transferred Materials, 1905-1926.
Scope and Contents
Series I and II of the Charles M. Bakewell Papers came to Manuscripts and Archives in 1976, when Yale students Carleton Ealy, Joseph Johnson, and Larry Kaufman found them in the basement of Lawrance Hall.* Most of what they discovered were philosophical publications, which have been transferred to other parts of the library. The remaining papers (correspondence, manuscript notes and writings, and printed matter spanning the years 1897-1947) were arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and II. Writings and Miscellany. In 1979, Mrs. Richard Hooker, daughter of Charles Bakewell, withdrew the correspondence, which had been located in the first six boxes. Series II is composed of lecture notes on philosophical topics and other teaching materials, typescript and manuscript drafts of writings on philosophy and politics, reprints of published writings, writings by other persons on philosophy and politics, and bibliographic notecards.
In 1982, a small collection of Bakewell's papers was transferred from the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection to the Bakewell Papers, where it constitutes Series III, Transferred Materials. They include seven letters of May 1926 from members of the Yale community and others to Bakewell about his review of The Complete Works of Friedrich Nietzche, which were donated to Yale by Charles Bakewell in 1945, and a notebook about Greek literature and four letters from Hugo Munsterberg and G. H. Palmer, all donated in 1958 by Henry P. Bakewell and Mrs. Hooker.
In 1990, sixteen volumes of photographs were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Yale University Library stacks. According to gift labels on the albums, they were originally donated to the library by Bakewell in 1932. The albums contain photographs taken in Italy during the American Red Cross Commission of World War I, from 1917 to 1919. Bakewell probably used these photographs during the writing of his 1920 book, The Story of the American Red Cross in Italy, and a few of the photographs are reproduced in the book. The albums supplement Bakewell's book and poignantly demonstrate the condition of Italy and her refugees during the war. Additional research materials which also carry the 1932 gift labels and document American Red Cross efforts in Italy during World War I were transferred in 2004.
* Yale Alumni Magazine 39 (1976), 38-39.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Montague Bakewell, professor of philosophy in Yale University and political and civic leader in Connecticut, was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, on April 24, 1867, the son of Thomas and Josephine Alden (Maitland) Bakewell. He was a descendant of Benjamin Bakewell, who migrated from England to New Haven, Connecticut, in 1794, and of Timothy Alden, who founded Allegheny College. Thomas Bakewell moved with his family from Pennsylvania to California in 1886, at which time Charles transferred from the Western University of Pennsylvania to the University of California. He received his M.A. in 1891 and then continued his graduate studies at Harvard University. Having received his Ph.D in 1894, he completed his training at the Universities of Berlin, Strasbourg, and Paris between 1894 and 1896.
After teaching for one year at Harvard, Bakewell was appointed instructor in philosophy at the University of California in 1897. He came back east to teach at Bryn Mawr between 1898 and 1900, but then returned to Berkeley and remained there until 1905. In that year he was appointed professor of philosophy at Yale. He assumed the Sheldon Clark Chair three years later and held that position until his retirement in 1933. His philosophical publications were Source Book in Ancient Philosophy; editions of Plato, Emerson, William James, and Thomas Davidson; and many articles for professional philosphers and educated popular audiences. He was elected president of the American Philosophical Association in 1910.
Bakewell's interest in public service was a natural extension of his outlook as a teacher and philosopher, but he became prominent outside the academy only in the second half of his career. His 1913 lecture at the Naval War College, "Moral Training in Preparation for War," was published the following year. His article, "The Philosophy of War and Peace," appeared in The Bookman in May 1917. The following year he went to Italy as inspector and historian for the Italian Commission of the American Red Cross and he completed this assignment by publishing The Story of the American Red Cross in Italy.
Bakewell first ran for public office in 1920, when he was elected as a Republican to the Connecticut State Senate. He became chairman of the General Assembly's Committee on Education and served on the Committee on Public Health and Safety. Re-elected in 1922, he retained his chairmanship of the Committee on Education and was also appointed to the newly established Commission on Revision and Codification of the School Laws. After he left the senate, successive governors appointed him to the State Board of Healing Arts and the Commission to Investigate Pension Systems for Municipalities.
In the 1920s, Bakewell was also a civic leader. As he explained to Morris R. Cohen, "ever since my year in Italy during the War, the Italians of New Haven adopted me," (October 1923), and he frequently addressed meetings of their fraternal organizations. He was active in the Lions, helping to found the New Haven chapter and serving on the international board of directors. He also helped organize the Connecticut division of the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, serving on the New Haven voluntary committee and the state executive committee.
Bakewell climaxed his political career by serving one term as Connecticut representative-at-large in the United States Congress. A vigorous opponent of the New Deal, he was defeated for re-election in 1934.
In 1899 Bakewell married Madeline Palmer, daughter of Henry W. Palmer, Pennsylvania attorney general and United States congressman. They had three children – Henry Palmer, Mildred Palmer (now Mrs. Richard Hooker), and Bradley Palmer. Charles Bakewell died in New Haven on September 19, 1957. He was survived by his children Henry and Mildred.
Education -- United States; Italian Americans -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Italians -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Philosophy; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Connecticut; New Haven (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.) -- Politics and government; World War, 1914-1918 -- Italy; Photographs; Educators; Politicians; Bakewell, Charles M. (Charles Montague), 1867-1957; American National Red Cross; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Philosophy Department
- Writings and Miscellany, 1897-1928, undated; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The papers are arranged in this order: lecture notes, miscellaneous teaching material, philosophical writings, civic and political writings, reprints, writings by persons other than Bakewell, bibliography, examination questions, political printed matter.
  These papers may only be used with permission of Mrs. Mildred Bakewell Hooker.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material in Series II may be used only with the permission of Mildred Bakewell Hooker, daughter of Charles Bakewell.
  - "Introductory": notes (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Thales": notes (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Anaximander": notes (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Anaximedes": notes (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Heraclitus": notes (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Pythagoras and the Pythagoreans": notes (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Xenophanes": notes (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Parmenides": notes (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Zeno and Melissus": notes (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Empedocles": notes (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Anaxagoras": notes (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Leucippos and Democritus": notes (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "The Sophists": notes (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "Socrates": notes (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "The Lesser Socratics": notes (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - "Plato and the Argument for Immortality": notes (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Plato": notes (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - "Aristotle": notes (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Aristotle—Categories: notes (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - "Stoics": notes (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Epicureans": notes (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "Alexandrine Period": notes (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - "Middle Ages": notes (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - "Bacon": notes (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - "Descartes": notes (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - "Spinoza": notes (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - "Leibniz": notes (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - "Locke": notes (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - "Berkeley": notes (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - "Hume": notes (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - "Kant": notes (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - "Later Modern Idealism": notes (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - "Political Philosophy": notes (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - "Hegel" notes (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - "Modern French Philosophy": notes (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - (Introductory course?), III-XXVI: notes (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Philosophy 12: syllabus and examination (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Yale Graduate School, Division III: notes of meetings, 1916-1920 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - "Aristotle": typescript (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - "George Berkeley": typescript (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - "Berkeley's Philosophy": typescript (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - "Ralph Waldo Emerson": typescript (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - "Emerson": typescript (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - "The Philosophy of Emerson": typescript (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Harry Norman Gardiner: manuscript obituaries (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - "Immanuel Kant": typescript (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - "The Ontological and Kant's Treatment of It": typescript (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Nietzsche: typescript fragments (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - "Plato": typescript (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - "The influence of Plato": typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 50)
  - "The Tragedy of Renan's Life": typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Josiah Royce: typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Socrates: typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - "Over-teaching and Under-teaching"; manuscript (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - "The Experiment of Democracy": manuscript (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - "Faith Cure of Pessimism": manuscript (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - "Stace's Cellology": manuscript (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - "The Continuity of the Idealist Tradition": typescript (Box 9, Folder 58 - 59)
  - "The Subject: What the Future Has in Store for the Churches, and What the Churches Have in Store for the Future": manuscript (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - "Art and Ideas": typescript (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - "Philosophy Goes to War": typescript (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - "The Tragic Philosophy": typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - The scientific view of nature: typescript fragment (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - "Suggested Questions in Hist. of Philos.": manuscript (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - American Red Cross in Italy: speeches (in Italian) and miscellaneous papers, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Address on Italian-American friendship: manuscript (in Italian) (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - New Haven political speech: manuscript (in Italian) (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Miscellaneous civic and political subjects: notes (Box 9, Folder 69 - 71)
  - The study of philosophy, Yale Daily News, April 16, 1914 [clipping] (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Letter to the editor of the Philadelphia Public Ledger (about M. Carey Thomas), April 13, 1916 [clipping] (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Reprints
    - 1897-1902 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - 1903-1905 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - 1907 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - 1908-1916 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - 1917-1926 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - 1927-1928, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - The philosophy of Thomas Davidson: notes by someone other than Charles Bakewell (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Drama reviews: drafts by Madeline Palmer Bakewell (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Konstantin Schlottheim, "The Perishable and the Imperishable in the Human Soul": translation by Arthur E. Little (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Bibliographic note cards (Box 11)
  - Examination questions (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous political publications by persons other than Charles M. Bakewell (Box 12–13)
- Transferred Materials, 1905-1926; Series III
  The correspondence in this series is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Angell, James Rowland, 1926 May 15 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Gardiner, Henry N., 1926 May 27 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1926 May 24 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Hibben, John Grier, 1926 May 11 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Jones, Frederick S., 1926 May 22 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Miller, Dickinson S., 1926 May 8 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Munsterberg, Hugo, 1905 December 8, 1906 March 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Palmer, G. H, 1916 November 22, 1922 March 27 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Tufts, James H., 1926 May 15 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Notebook on Greek literature, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1917-1919; Accession 1990-M-066
  These sixteen photograph albums cover the work of the American Red Cross (ARC) in Italy during World War I. The majority are arranged into albums named by geographic location, while others are named for their topical content.
  The photographs depict scenes recorded during the ARC Commission in Italy, most of them taken between late 1917 and early 1919. There is no indication that Bakewell was the photographer, but the snapshots were unmistakably made by individuals working within the Commission, and Bakewell's contact with them most likely enabled him to obtain them. All of the photographs are labelled clearly and consistently. A good description of the albums is included in a report in the first folder of the accession which identifies key photographs and their locations in the albums.
  Typical images depicted in the photographs are Italian refugees (especially children); villagers in traditional costume; children receiving lessons and doing exercises; soldiers at rest; ARC nurses, doctors and workers, and officers at work; high ranking persons within the ARC as well as President Woodrow Wilson, King Vittoreo Emmanuele, and Ernest Hemingway; distribution scenes; refugees eating and waiting in lines for food and supplies; ambulances and rolling canteens; and speeches, holidays and ceremonies. Common locations pictured include hospitals, military rest stations, soup kitchens, asylums, interiors and exteriors of warehouses, schools, workrooms of all kinds, beach scenes, town ruins, and roads and buildings under reconstruction.
  (Addition inventory by Carol King.)
  - "The Bakewell Collection of World War I photographs at Yale University Library," report by Kristen Hacken (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume 1. Rimini, Ancona (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume 2. Persons: Colonel Perkins, King and others (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Volume 3. Sardinia (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Volume 4. Roman district-1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Volume 5. Roman district and Rome-2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Volume 6. Invaded territory (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Volume 7. Florence, including Leghorn and Lucca Spreziano Colony (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Volume 8. Piedmont, Lombardy (including Turin, Milan, rice fields, Varedo, Monza) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Volume 9. Genoa (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Volume 10. Italian troops #1, ambulances, rolling canteens, station canteens, rest houses, gift distribution (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Volume 11. Italian troops #2, ambulances, rolling canteens, station canteen, rest houses, gift distribution (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Volume 12. Sicily, Calabria (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Volume 13. Venice, Padua (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Volume 14. Naples, Avellino (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Volume 15. Avellino (continued) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Volume 16. American troops (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Additional Material, 1917-1920; Accession 2004-M-090
  This accession consists of research materials used by Bakewell in support of The Story of the American Red Cross in Italy. It is arranged by format into four sections: account ledger, card file, photographs, and research files.
  The account ledger lists the total appropriations and disbursements for the entire operation from July to December 1918, and shows departmental appropriations and disbursements from November 1917 to December 1918. Departments included are administration, civil affairs, military affairs, medical affairs, and tuberculosis. For each department, operational expenses of all kinds are recorded along with disbursement records.
  The card file contains informational research cards that Bakewell presumably used in the process of writing the book. Each card is headed by one of sixteen designated geographic locations (district, city, or village) by which the cards have been arranged, and the activities of American Red Cross (ARC) distribution centers, creches (day nurseries for children), schools, and asilos (asylums) in and around that location are divided and summarized by topic and subtopic. These cards are an excellent source of quick information, recording monthly summaries of facts relating to each facility, such as hours or seasons of operation, number of beds, amount and type of clothing or food distributed, how many refugees served, cost per person, and materials produced by refugee labor. In addition to data, the cards contain narrative accounts of the ARC workers and Italians who received their assistance.
  There are approximately one hundred fifty photographs of various sizes, mostly 5 by 8 inches. Some are enlarged duplicates of photographs contained in the albums in the previous accession, but many are unique. Highlights include images of Italian refugees, especially children at the asilos, ARC workers and volunteers administering care and teaching, and the work camps where refugees were taught skills that helped sustain the stations. Other common scenes depict children at Italian beaches, ARC ambulances in the terrain, rolling canteens, rest stations, American troops being welcomed by Italians, ARC officers, and Italian locations and monuments.
  Finally, included in this addition are eight oversize broadsides with Italian text which Bakewell had labelled "Manifesti."
  - Account ledger, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Card file, [1917-1919] (Box 2)
  - Photographs, [1917-1919] (Box 2)
  - By geographic area or camp name (Box 3, Folder 1 - 6)
    - Ambulances and stations (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - American Red Cross officers [unlabeled] (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - American troops (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Refugees [mostly unlabeled] (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Research files
    - Administration, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ambulance [reports, clippings, and manuscript], 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 12 - 13)
    - American Relief Clearing House, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Asili [letters of appreciation], 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Baker Commission, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Campidoglio meeting, [1917-1919] (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Canteens, 1918, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Children's homes [institutions for children], [1917-1919] (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Children, relief of [Mrs. Springer's report], [ca. 1918] (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Civil Affairs Department, Summary of Activities" [Mrs. Springer's report], 1918 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Clippings from bulletins and newspapers, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Colosseum celebration, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Davison, Henry P. [regarding visit to Italy], 1918 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Decorations to Red Cross personnel, 1918, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Delegates [suggestions and instructions for], 1919, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Department reports, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Emergency commission, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Emergency relief [Mrs. Springer's report], [ca. 1918] (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - General reports on Red Cross activities, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Home service [to American soldiers], [ca. 1918] (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Instructions to American Red Cross personnel [clippings], [1918] (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Italian agencies, assistance to [Mrs. Springer's report], [ca. 1918] (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Italian organizations, assistance to [pamphlet and clippings], [1918-1919?] (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Italian army, 1918, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Italian Red Cross [clippings], 1918 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Italians working for American Red Cross [personal narratives], [1918?] (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Japanese Red Cross, visit of [clipping], [ca. 1918 or 1919] (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - June Offensive, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - McKey, Edward M., death of, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - "Medical and Surgical Supplies Delivered from Rome" [report], 1918 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Milan 3280 ["from Major Hereford"], 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Militarization of American Red Cross, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Monthly distribution to soldiers' families, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Pamphlets [ La Battaglia di Vittorio Veneto, Cucine Gratuite, Financial Report of the American Relief Clearing House in Rome, In Onore della Croce Americana, Modern Italy, Report and Supplement of the Department of Medical Affairs, The Rockefeller Foundation: A Review, Seven Weeks in Italy ], 1917- 1920 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Personnel
      - Alphabetical listing, [ca. 1919] (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Ambulance service sections one to five, [ca. 1919] (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Commissioned officers of the American Red Cross in Italy, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Department of Tuberculosis, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - High-profile individuals in American Red Cross, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - Italian Commission of American Red Cross, [ca. 1919] (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - Nurses enrolled in Italy, [1919] (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - Organization by departments [annotated], 1918 and [1919] (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Salonica, Colonel E. W. Ryan [Serbian border], [1917?] (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Staff listed by district, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Pisa, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Refugees, [1918] (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Rest Houses -Casa del Soldato [distribution of gifts], 1918 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Rolling canteen reports [cucine reports 1-10, Vicenza], 1918 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Rolling canteens [narratives], 1918 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Soldier's families, distribution to Italians [Mrs. Springer's report], 1918 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Spring cash distribution, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Translations [Italian reports and news items to English], 1917-1920 (Box 6, Folder 63 - 66)
    - "Trip to the Front by an American Girl", 1918 (Box 6, Folder 67)